Guide to the Dorothy Peterson Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dorothy Peterson collection
1919-1966
JWJ MSS 10
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.6
(5 boxes)
The Dorothy Peterson Collection contains Correspondence to Peterson from such persons as Langston Hughes, Nella Larsen, and Carl Van Vechten.
Peterson, Dorothy
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Dorothy Peterson Collection contains items presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection by Ms. Peterson and friends of hers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Correspondence with Rudolph Fisher and Jean Toomer is restricted. Please consult the appropriate curator for further information.
DOROTHY PETERSON
Dorothy Peterson was a teacher of Spanish at Wadleigh High School in New York City. She was involved in the Harlem writers' scene with such organizations as the Negro Actors' Guild, continuing the commitment to African-American causes shown by her father, noted journalist Jerome Peterson.
Scope and Contents
The Dorothy Peterson Collection contains Correspondence to Peterson from such persons as Langston Hughes, Nella Larsen, and Carl Van Vechten.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Larsen, Nella, 1891-1964; Peterson, Dorothy; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
- Correspondence, 1942-53; Series I
  - A-M General correspondence, 1942-53 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    To: 28 / From: 0
  - Alexander, Scholley Pace, 1928, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    To: 2 / From: 0
  - American Council of African Education, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barthé, Richmond, 1956-59, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    To: 6 / From: 0
  - Boardman, Helen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Biographical eulogy "Jerome B. Peterson: A Negro Friend"
  - Bontemps, Arna, 1944-57 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To: 9 / From: 0
  - Bosley, Roberta, 1945-46 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    To: 5 / From: 0
  - Butler, Elizabeth, 1949 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    To: 0 / From: 1
  - Byrne, Margaret C., 1943-46 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Campbell, Constance [Mrs. E. Sims], 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    To: 3 / From: 0
  - Carter, Elmer A.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Negro Actors Guild, Box 2, folder 34
  - Connelly, Marc, 1930 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    To: 1 / From: 0
  - Cullen, Countee, 1927-45 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes review of Knowlton Mixer's Porto Rico by Dorothy Peterson and letter to Carl Van Vechten from DP
    To: 7 / From: 0
  - Delany, Hubert T., 1945 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ewing, Max, 1933 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fisher, Rudolph, 1919-28
    See: RESTRICTED CORRESPONDENCE, Box 5, folder 74
  - Harris, Dorothy, 1930 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Harrison, Richard B., 1933, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes correspondence with Harrison, Laurence (To: 1 / From: 1)
  - Hays, Arthur Garfield, 1946 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hill, Leemar A., 1943-45 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1926-59 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    To: 16 / From: 0
    Includes: "A House in Taos," "Greetings for Canada Lee," "The Ballad of Dorrie Miller," "Here to Yonder: Noblesse Oblige" and"The Christmas Story" by LH
  - Hull, Elizabeth, ca. 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jackman, Harold, 1929, 1933, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    To: 4 / From: 0
  - Johnson, Charles, 1928-56 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Johnson, Georgia Douglas, 1946 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Johnson, James Weldon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Johnson, J. Rosamond
    See: Negro Actor's Guild, Box 2, folder 34
  - Larsen, Nella, 1927, 1933, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lewis, Theophilus, 1929 Jan 22 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Locke, Alain, 1929 Feb (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Includes letter from Locke to Alexander Scholley Pace
  - Lutz, Mark, 1964-66, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    To: 0 / From: 16
  - McClendon, Rose, 1932 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Morris, Newbold, 1944 Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - N-Z General correspondence, 1943-56 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Namara, Marguerite, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Negro Actors Guild, 1945-46 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Letters signed by Elmer A. Carter, J. Rosamond Johnson, Mabel A. Roane and Noble Sissle
    To: 33 / From: 0
  - Nugent, Bruce, 1928-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    To: 8 / From: 0
  - Peterson, Carla, 1953-58, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Peterson, Danna, 1951-59, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    To: 26 / From: 0
  - Peterson, Jane, 1952-59, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    To: 15 / From: 0
  - Peterson, Jerome S. [Sid], 1946 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Peterson, Vera, 1954, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Reckling, Frances Kraft, 1946 Feb 2 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Redding, Saunders, 1956 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Robeson, Paul, 1943 Dec 9 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Rutherford, Thomas, 1936-42, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Includes letter from Snowball Crump
  - Schuyler, George, 1956 Sep 27 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Sissle, Noble
  - Southwest Harlem Neighborhood Council, Inc., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Toomer, Jean, 1925-1934
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1925-41 (Box 2, Folder 47-52)
    To: 105 / From: 0
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1942-54 (Box 3, Folder 53-65)
    To: 215 / From: 2
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1954-59, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 66-69)
    To: 101 / From: 0
  - White, Walter, 1944 Jun 21 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Wright, Richard, 1940 Sep 15 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Yurka, Blanche, 1945 Mar 18 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Unidentified correspondents, 1942, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 73)
- RESTRICTED CORRESPONDENCE, 1919-28
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Fisher, Rudolph, 1919-28 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    14 letters
  - Toomer, Jean, 1925-1934 (Box 5, Folder 75-76)
    27 letters